Merrimac, Mass. Pilgrim Congregational Church records, 1725-1900.
Congregational Library Archives
Merrimac, Mass. Pilgrim Congregational Church records, 1725-1900.
RG0123
Congregational Library Archives
0.88 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes)
Parish organized in 1725; church founded in 1726 as Second Church of Christ in Amesbury, Mass. Merrimac separated from Amesbury in 1876 and in 1879 the church became the First Congregational Church, popularly known as Pilgrim Congregational Church. In 1879 the First Orthodox Congregational Society was incorporated, replacing the earlier West Parish Congregational Society. The First Orthodox Congregational Church of Merrimac was incorporated in 1894 and the First Orthodox Congregational Society was dissolved. Extant as Pilgrim Congregational UCC in 1996. This collection consists of church and parish records and miscellaneous papers, including deeds, ordination papers, and printed materials. Includes diary of Rev. Paine Wingate, minister from 1726-1782, with added vital statistics to 1789 and ecclesiastical functions of Amesbury, Mass. West Parish, Second Congregational Society.
First Congregational Society of Merrimac
Pilgrim Congregational Church (Merrimac, Mass.)
Second Church of Christ (Amesbury, Mass.)
Wingate, Paine
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Placed on permanent loan with the Congregational Library & Archives in February 1987 by the Pilgrim Congregational Church, Merrimac, Massachusetts.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Historical Note
The parish was first organized in 1725 and a year later the church itself was founded as the Second Church of Christ in Amesbury. The town of Merrimac separated from Amesbury in 1876 and in 1879 the church was renamed to the First Congregational Church, though it was popularly referred to as the Pilgrim Congregational Church. Also in 1879, the First Orthodox Congregational Society was incorporated, replacing the earlier West Parish Congregational Society. The First Orthodox Congregational Church of Merrimac was incorporated in 1894 and the First Orthodox Congregational Society was dissolved.
The church continues to serve the Merrimac community as the Pilgrim Congregational Church.
Scope and Contents
The Merrimac Mass. Pilgrim Congregational Church records document the history, administration, and life of the church and the social life town residents. The types of records include membership lists and certificates of membership to religious societies, baptismal records, marriage records, death records, church and parish meeting minutes, financial documents, church publications, land deeds, a will, pew deeds, subscription lists, records related to the building and expansion of church property, and the diary of the first minister, Paine Wingate.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by chronological order, when possible, and by topic.
Technical Requirements
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
Baptism and church membership.; Baptismal records.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Diaries.; Marriage records.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Pews and pew rights.; Wills.; Amesbury (Mass.) -- Church history.; First Congregational Society of Merrimac; Merrimac (Mass.) -- Church history.; Pilgrim Congregational Church (Merrimac, Mass.); Second Church of Christ (Amesbury, Mass.)
- Book of Records in Amesbury, 1725 1848; 1725-1848 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  Digital Copies
  These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
  Scope and Contents
  The Book of Records in Amesbury includes annual meeting minutes, records of payment for the minister's annual salary, parish meeting minutes, records of votes, records of officer selection, minutes for meetings related to Reverend Wingate's contract, pew sales, calls for town meetings, and tax collector appointments.
- Church Records, 1726 1782; 1726-1782 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  These Church records include records pertaining to the formation of the church, ordination records, records of votes, payments made, church meeting minutes, list of members who came from another church, list of members taken into full communion, and marriage records.
- Paine Wingate Book, 1726 1821; 1726-1821 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  The Paine Wingate Book contains largely church records, but also some personal records. Included within these records are the church's Articles of Faith, church meeting minutes, payment records, personal diary entries related to church members and church activities, records of dismission from the church, records of votes, list of ordinations, list of administrants of Last Supper, a list of members who joined from other churches, a list of members taken into full communion, death records, vital records for the Wingate family, baptismal records, and a list of members who renewed their baptismal covenant.
  Separated Materials
  The final will and testament of Paine Wingate was folded and placed in the back of this volume. It was removed, flattened, and placed in its own folder for preservation purposes.
- Church Records, 1788 1843; 1788-1843 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  These church records include a date of purchase, church meeting minutes, records of votes, ecclesiastical council meeting minutes, church communications, ordination records, baptismal records, members lists, marriage records, and death records.
- Tax and Account Book, 1812 1883; 1812-1883 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  This volume contains 312 pages of financial records dating from 1812-1883. Included within these records are payment records, records related to salary, payments and taxes collected by the church, the church ledger, accounts for membership dues, and lists of names with their individual tax burdens.
- Records of the Second Congregational Church of Amesbury, 1842 1894; 1842-1894 (Box 1, Volume 5)
- Deed to Parsonage Lands, 1747 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Selection of Minister, 1842 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Annual Meeting Officer Selection, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Publications, 1844 1918; 1844-1918 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Wingate Will, 1777; 1 Item (Box 2, Folder 5)
  This is the final will and testament of Paine Wingate and includes ten clauses related to how his property, money, and livestock were to be divided among his family.
- Parish Records, 1743 1788; 1743-1788; 51 Items (Box 2, Folder 6)
  These parish records are loose documents covering various parish activities. Included in the records are financial documents, records of votes, church and parish meeting minutes, subscribers meeting minutes, calls to assembly, certificates of membership, and certificates of office.
- Parish Records, 1790 1839; 1790-1839; 33 Items (Box 2, Folder 7)
  This folder contains 104 pages of loose parish records. Included in the records are financial documents, records of votes, church and parish meeting minutes, subscribers meeting minutes, calls to assembly, and a list of subscribers.
- Payments and Taxes, 1781 1829; 1781-1829 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- First Baptist Society Membership, 1806 1833; 1806-1833; 16 Items (Box 2, Folder 9)
  This folder contains 32 pages of loose documents. Included in the folder are early membership lists for the First Baptist Society, certificates of membership for individuals, and an 1814 petition to the Massachusetts legislature to form a religious society.
- Second Baptist Society Membership, 1824 1833; 1824-1833; 22 Items (Box 2, Folder 10)
  This folder contains 44 pages of loose documents. Included in the folder are certificates of membership to the Second Baptist Society.
- Methodist Society Membership, 1826 1932; 1826-1832; 7 Items (Box 2, Folder 11)
  This folder contains 14 pages of loose documents. Included in the folder are certificates of membership to the Methodist Society.
- Universalist Society Membership, 1833; 3 Items (Box 2, Folder 12)
  This folder contains 6 pages of loose documents. Included in the folder are certificates of membership to the Universalist Society.
- Parsonage Construction, 1828 1829; 1828-1829 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- New Meeting House, 1836 1840; 1836-1840 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Pew Deeds, 1839 1900; 1839-1900 (Box 2, Folder 15)